John Hay Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John Hay Papers 1783-1999 1897-1905
MSS25379
Hay, John, 1838-1905
11,300 items
36 containers plus 40 oversize
29 linear feet
23 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Statesman, diplomat, historian, journalist, and poet. Correspondence and letterbooks, speeches, diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, and memoranda, mainly for the years 1897-1905 when Hay served as United States ambassador to Great Britain and United States secretary of state. Earlier papers deal with his legal, literary, and journalistic activities and with his service as assistant secretary to Abraham Lincoln. Includes correspondence of his wife, Clara Louise Stone Hay (1849-1914), for the years 1882-1914.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, Brooks, 1848-1927--Correspondence.; Adee, Alvey A. (Alvey Augustus), 1842-1924--Correspondence.; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917--Correspondence.; Cortelyou, George B. (George Bruce), 1862-1940--Correspondence.; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926--Correspondence.; Hay family.; Hay, Clara Louise Stone, 1849-1914 Clara Louise Stone Hay correspondence. 1882-1914.; Hay, John, 1838-1905.; James, Henry, 1843-1916--Correspondence.; King, Clarence, 1842-1901--Correspondence.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924--Correspondence.; McKinley, William, 1843-1901--Correspondence.; McKinley, William, 1843-1901.; Pauncefote, Julian, 1828-1902--Correspondence.; Rockhill, William Woodville, 1854-1914--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Spring Rice, Cecil, Sir, 1859-1918--Correspondence.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910--Correspondence.
Subjects
American newspapers--New York (State).; American poetry.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Great Britain.; Land grants--Kentucky.; Practice of law--Illinois--Springfield.; Slavery--United States.; Spanish-American War, 1898.
Places
Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1897-1901.; United States--Foreign relations--1901-1909.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Titles
New York tribune.
Occupations
Authors.; Cabinet officers.; Diplomats.; Journalists.; Poets.; Statesmen.
Acquisition Information
The papers of John Hay, statesman, diplomat, historian, journalist, and poet, were given to the Library of Congress in 1952 by Hay's son and daughter, Clarence L. Hay and Alice Hay Wadsworth. Additional material was received from his grandchildren, Evelyn Wadsworth Symington (Mrs. Stuart Symington), Reverdy Wadsworth, and James J. Wadsworth, in 1960 and from James W. Symington in 1999, 2003, and 2008. A few items also were obtained through gift, purchase, and transfer between 1910 and 1942.
Transfers
A broadside was transferred to the Rare Book and Special Collections Division where it is identified as part of these papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact the Rare Book and Special Collections Division in advance of a research visit.
Other Repositories
Other papers of John Hay can be found in the John Hay Library of Brown University at Providence, Rhode Island.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the Tyler Dennett Collection Relating to John Hay (see https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms007069), the Evelyn Wadsworth Symington Collection of John Hay Material (see https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms011121), and the James Wadsworth Family Papers (see https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms997014).
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John Hay are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on twenty-three reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1838, Oct. 8 Born, Salem, Ind.
1858 Graduated, Brown University, Providence, R.I.
1859 Entered law office of Milton Hay, Springfield, Ill.
1861 1864 Assistant private secretary to Abraham Lincoln
1864 1865 Assistant adjutant general in the United States Army
1865 1867 Secretary of American legation, Paris, France
1867 1868 Charge d'affaires, Vienna, Austria
1869 1870 Secretary of American legation, Madrid, Spain
1870 1875 Editorial writer, New York Tribune
1874 Married Clara Louise Stone (died 1914)
1879 1881 Assistant secretary of state
1881 Editor, New York Tribune
1897 1898 Ambassador to Great Britain
1898 1905 Secretary of state
1905, July 1 Died, Lake Sunapee, N.H.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Hay (1838-1905) span the years 1783 to 1999, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1897-1905. The collection focuses on his diplomatic efforts as secretary of state but also contains material on his career before 1898 and on his personal life. It is composed mainly of correspondence, scrapbooks, and newspaper clippings supplemented by diaries, letterbooks, and miscellaneous material. There is also an autograph collection relating chiefly to slavery in the United States.
American diplomacy from 1898 to 1905 is the central theme of the Diaries and Notebooks and various correspondence series. As secretary of state during the period, Hay played a crucial role in the formulation and execution of American foreign policy. The diaries reflect Hay's role in the later years of his tenure in office. The Letterbooks and John Hay Letters series reveal his views and activities in the diplomatic sphere under presidents William McKinley and Theodore Roosevelt. Hay's letters to his wife in the Family Correspondence series, although primarily concerned with personal and social activities, also provide an occasional glimpse into his official concerns.
The Special Correspondence and General Correspondence series provide information on all aspects of American foreign affairs while Hay was secretary of state and are useful in portraying his nondiplomatic activities as well. The letters from American diplomatic agents throughout the world reveal the conditions in various countries that influenced official American policy and the manner in which policy decisions were implemented. The largest number of letters in this category are from Joseph Choate and William W. Rockhill in the Special Correspondence. Hay's correspondence with Roosevelt and Alvey A. Adee, among others, provides an intimate glimpse into the formation of policy. The Special Correspondence and General Correspondence series also help to elucidate Hay's personal and political concerns.
The container list includes an index to the Special Correspondence series. Included among the correspondents are Brooks Adams, Samuel L. Clemens, George B. Cortelyou, Charles William Eliot, Henry James, Clarence King, Henry Cabot Lodge (1850-1924), William McKinley, Julian Pauncefote, Elihu Root, and Cecil Spring-Rice.
A Miscellany series contains autographs, drawings, invitations, notes, photographs, printed matter, receipted bills, research material, speeches, and writings. Included is a vellum copy of the Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution autographed by the signators of the amendment.
The Scrapbooks series contains newspaper clippings dealing with America's participation in the Spanish-American War and Hay's personal and political activities, particularly from 1898 to 1905.
The Additions includes a land grant issued by the state of Kentucky on July 2, 1798, to Abraham Lincoln (1744-1786), grandfather of President Abraham Lincoln, and his heirs, along with a letter of January 5, 1877, to John G. Nicolay from A. C. Matthews concerning the grant and a report documenting its authenticity. Also included is a scrapbook containing photographs and newspaper clippings relating to diplomatic functions and family occasions. The 2008 Addition contains a letter from Elizabeth Marion Bryce to Clara Louise Stone Hay concerning a gift of a drawing of the Andes mountain range. The 2021 Addition includes three letters from Hay to his daughter, Alice Hay Wadsworth, concerning personal and social activities. In one letter, Hay recounts his first visit to Victoria, Queen of Great Britain. Two other letters are addressed to Hay and relate to the recent death of the queen in 1901.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eleven series:
Diaries and Notebooks, 1861-1908
Letterbooks, 1898-1905
John Hay Letters, 1858-1905
Family Correspondence, 1882-1914
Special Correspondence, 1885-1913
Autograph Collection, 1783-1878
General Correspondence, 1856-1905
Miscellany, 1802-1953
Scrapbooks, 1860-1905
Additions, 1798-1999
Oversize, 1783-1905
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 15,213
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1861-1908 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Diaries and notebooks containing occasional copies of letters, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and a negative photostat of the key to the printed edition of Letters of John Hay and Extracts from Diary, selected by Henry Adams and edited by Clara Louise Stone Hay, 1908.
  - Diaries, 1904-1906, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Notebooks, 1861-1868, 1878, undated, (2 folders)
  - Key to printed edition of Letters of John Hay and Extracts from Diary, selected by Henry Adams and edited by Clara Louise Stone Hay, 1908
- Letterbooks, 1898-1905 (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
  Bound volumes of copies of letters sent by Hay.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1898-1905, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
- John Hay Letters, 1858-1905 (Box 3-5, Reel 3-4)
  Holograph and typed letters and holograph, typed, and photostatic copies of letters sent by Hay.
  - 1858-1899, (12 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - 1900
    - Jan.-Sept., (2 folders)
    - Oct.-Dec. (Box 4, Reel 3-4)
  - 1901-1902, (8 folders)
  - 1903
    - Jan.-Oct., (4 folders)
    - Nov.-Dec. (Box 5, Reel 4)
  - 1904-1905, undated, (9 folders)
- Family Correspondence, 1882-1914 (Box 6-7, Reel 5-6)
  Letters from Hay to his wife, Clara Louise Stone Hay; letters received and occasional letters sent by Clara Louise Stone Hay; and one bound volume of letters to her.
  The John Hay letters are separated from the Clara Louise Stone Hay correspondence, and both groups are arranged chronologically.
  - Hay, John, to Clara Louise Stone Hay, 1894-1905, undated, (5 folders) (Box 6, Reel 5)
  - Hay, Clara Louise Stone, letters received and sent
    - Unbound
      - 1882-1904, (4 folders)
      - 1905
        - Jan.-June
        - July-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5)
      - 1907-1914, undated, (2 folders)
    - Bound, July 1905 See Oversize (Box 7, Reel 6)
- Special Correspondence, 1885-1913 (Box 8-13, Reel 6-9)
  Letters to John Hay and occasionally to his wife from prominent correspondents.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Adams, Brooks, 1897-1902 (Box 8, Reel 6)
  - Adee, Alvey A., 1897-1907, (10 folders)
  - Barnes, B., 1903-1904
  - Bigelow, William Sturgis, 1899-1904, undated
  - Bishop, Joseph Bucklin, 1892-1905, undated
  - Cameron, E. S., 1897-1898, undated (Box 9, Reel 6-7)
  - Carnegie, Andrew, 1898-1907, undated
  - Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1898-1905, (12 folders)
  - Clarke, John and Charlotte, 1891-1907, undated (Box 10, Reel 7-8)
  - Clemens, Samuel L., 1899-1904
  - Cortelyou, George B., 1899-1905, (6 folders)
  - Davis, L. Clarke and Rebecca Harding, 1900-1904 (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Davis, Richard Harding, 1900-1901, undated
  - Eddy, Spencer, 1901-1905
  - Eliot, Charles William, 1899-1903
  - Elliot, Henry Ware, 1899-1905, undated
  - Griscom, Lloyd Carpenter and Clement A., 1899-1905
  - Hanna, Marcus Alonzo, 1895-1903, undated (Box 11, Reel 8)
  - James, Henry, 1897-1907, undated [letter of 18 Dec. 1903, James to Hay, verso of page five not on microfilm]
  - King, Clarence, 1891, undated
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot (1850-1924), 1898-1907, undated
  - Loeb, William (1866-1937), 1901-1905, (5 folders)
  - McKinley, William, 1897-1901, undated
  - Mason, Frank H., 1897-1905
  - Montgomery, Benjamin F., 1900-1901
  - Morgan, Edwin V., 1899-1905, undated
  - Pauncefote, Julian, 1897-1902, undated, (3 folders) (Box 12, Reel 9)
  - Porter, John Addison, 1897-1900, (2 folders)
  - Rhodes, James Ford, 1885-1907, undated
  - Rockhill, William W., 1898-1904, undated, (4 folders)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (1858-1919), 1897-1907, (3 folders)
  - Root, Elihu, 1899-1913, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13, Reel 9)
  - Shanks, William Franklin Gore, 1898-1904
  - Spring-Rice, Cecil, Sir, 1891-1905, undated, (2 folders)
  - Stanton, Theodore, 1902-1904, undated
  - Stover, Bellamy and Maria, 1898-1903, undated
  - Winter, William, 1898-1904
- Autograph Collection, 1783-1878 (Box 13, Reel 10)
  A bound volume entitled “From Congo to Congress” containing original and facsimile correspondence, autographs, clippings, notices, and documents relating generally to slavery in the United States.
  - “From Congo to Congress” See Oversize (Box 13, Reel 10)
- General Correspondence, 1856-1905 (Box 14-29, Reel 10-21)
  Letters received.
  - 1856-1898, (12 folders) (Box 14, Reel 10-11)
  - 1899 (Box 15, Reel 11)
    - Jan.-June, (11 folders)
    - July-Dec., (11 folders) (Box 16, Reel 11-12)
  - 1900 (Box 17, Reel 12-13)
    - Jan.-June, (11 folders)
    - July-Dec., (12 folders) (Box 18, Reel 13)
  - 1901 (Box 19, Reel 13-14)
    - Jan.-June, (11 folders)
    - July-Dec., (13 folders) (Box 20, Reel 14-15)
  - 1902 (Box 21, Reel 15-16)
    - Jan.-June, (14 folders)
    - July-Dec., (13 folders) (Box 22, Reel 16)
  - 1903 (Box 23, Reel 17)
    - Jan.-May, (13 folders)
    - June-Sept., (12 folders) (Box 24, Reel 17-18)
    - Oct.-Dec., (10 folders) (Box 25, Reel 18)
  - 1904 (Box 26, Reel 18-19)
    - Jan.-Apr., (11 folders)
    - May-Aug., (13 folders) (Box 27, Reel 19-20)
    - Sept.-Dec., (14 folders) (Box 28, Reel 20-21)
  - 1905, undated, (11 folders) (Box 29, Reel 21)
- Miscellany, 1802-1953 (Box 30-36, Reel 21-23)
  Invitations, cards, and notices; John Hay writings, speeches, and research materials; materials compiled by Tyler Dennett about Hay; autograph album; printed matter including pamphlets and newspaper clippings; unbound photographs; and two photograph albums.
  Arranged by type of material. The newspaper clippings are not included on the microfilm.
  - Invitations, cards, and notices, 1864, 1880-1881, 1890, 1897-1905, undated, (9 folders); (8 folders) (Box 30, Reel 21, Box 31, Reel 21-22, Box 32, Reel 22)
  - Writings, speeches, and research material, 1863, 1875, 1892-1912, undated (Box 33, Reel 22)
  - Dennett, Tyler, research material regarding Hay, 1930-1931, undated
  - Drawings, notes, printed ephemera, receipted bills, and an autographed copy of the Thirteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, 1863-1868, 1897-1905, undated See also Oversize
  - Printed matter, 1898-1905 (Box 34, Reel 23)
  - Pamphlets, 1802, 1896-1905, 1953
  - Autograph album, 1877-1878
  - “Proposal for Second Peace Conference at the Hague,” 1904
  - Photographs (Box 35, Reel 23)
    - Album, undated
    - Unbound, 1904, undated
    - “President McKinley, California, and Buffalo,” 1901 See Oversize
  - “Maryland, My Maryland,” and cover letter by James R. Randall, 1887 See Oversize
  - “The Helmet of Mambrino, A Letter to Horace F. Cutter from Clarence King,” 1882 See Oversize
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1878-circa 1918, (5 folders); (6 folders) (Box 36)
- Scrapbooks, 1860-1905 (Box 36)
  Bound volumes of newspaper clippings relating generally to the Spanish-American War and American diplomacy.
  Arranged by subject and therein chronologically.
  - See Oversize (Box 36)
- Additions, 1798-1999 (Box 36)
  Correspondence, land grant, and scrapbook.
  Arranged by topic or type of material.
  - Addition (Box 36)
    - Correspondence, 1889-1893, 1913 (Box 36)
    - Lincoln, Abraham (1744-1786), land grant, 1798, 1887, 1999, (3 folders)
    - Scrapbook, 1837-1938 See Oversize
  - 2008 Addition, correspondence, 1913 (Box 36)
  - 2021 Addition, correspondence, 1897-1901
- Oversize, 1783-1905 (Box OV 1-OV 40)
  Autographs, historical documents, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed. Except for the scrapbook in the Addition, all items are available on the microfilm edition where they were filmed as listed in their original series.
  - Family Correspondence (Box OV 1)
    - Hay, Clara Louise Stone, letters received and sent
      - Bound, July 1905 (Container 7; Reel 6)
  - Autograph collection (Box OV 2)
    - “From Congo to Congress,” 1783-1878 (Container 13; Reel 10)
  - Miscellany (Box OV 3)
    - Drawings, notes, printed ephemera, receipted bills
      - Thirteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, 1864 (Container 33; Reel 22)
    - Photographs (Box OV 4)
      - “President McKinley, California, and Buffalo,” 1901 (Container 35; Reel 23)
    - “Maryland, My Maryland,” and cover letter by James R. Randall, 1887 (Container 35; Reel 23) (Box OV 5)
    - “The Helmet of Mambrino, A Letter to Horace F. Cutter from Clarence King,” 1882 (Container 35; Reel 23) (Box OV 6)
  - Scrapbooks (Box OV 7)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1860-1874 (Container 36), (2 vols.)
      - 1861-1882 (Container 36), (2 vols.) (Box OV 8)
      - 1871-1874 (Container 36), (2 vols.) (Box OV 9)
      - 1874-1890 (Container 36), (3 vols.) (Box OV 10)
      - 1891-1900 (Container 36), (3 vols.) (Box OV 11)
      - 1898 (Box OV 12)
      - 1900 (Container 36), (1 vol.); (3 vols.) (Box OV 13, Box OV 14, Box OV 15)
      - 1900-1901 (Container 36), (2 vols.)
      - 1901 (Container 36), (3 vols.) (Box OV 16, Box OV 17)
      - 1901-1902 (Container 36), (2 vols.) (Box OV 18)
      - 1902 (Container 36), (1 vol.); (2 vols.) (Box OV 19, Box OV 20)
      - 1902-1903 (Container 36) (Box OV 21)
      - 1903 (Container 36), (1 vol.); (2 vols.) (Box OV 22, Box OV 23, Box OV 24, Box OV 25)
      - 1903-1904 (Container 36)
      - 1904 (Container 36), (2 vols.) (Box OV 26, Box OV 27, Box OV 28, Box OV 29)
      - 1905 (Container 36), (2 vols.); (1 vol.) (Box OV 30, Box OV 31, Box OV 32)
    - Spanish-American War (Box OV 33)
      - 1897-1898 (Container 36), (2 vols.)
      - 1898 (Container 36), (2 vols.) (Box OV 34, Box OV 35, Box OV 36, Box OV 37, Box OV 38, Box OV 39)
  - Additions (Box OV 40)
    - Addition
      - Scrapbook, 1837-1938 (Container 36)